A Guide to the Virginia Secretary of Transportation, Correspondence and Subject Files, 1972-1977
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Virginia Secretary of Transportation, Correspondence and Subject Files, 1972-1977
The Library of Virginia
30059
6 cu. ft. (6 boxes)
Virginia. Office of the Secretary of Transportation
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Accession 30059 was transfered from the Office of the Secretary of Transportation by Wayne A. Whitham, on 25 July 1978 to the Virginia State Library and Archives for permanent retention.
Biographical Information
In 1970, the Governor's Management Commission Study recommended the creation of six "Deputy Governors" to assist the Chief Executive in his managerial duties. Compatible functions of government were grouped under these administrative heads, who would serve as the Governors top management team or "secretariats," as they are called now.
Governor Linwood Holton's top priority for the 1972 session of the General Assembly was a proposal for a Governor's Cabinet, reorganizing state agencies into six major departments--each headed by a secretary appointed by the governor. Transportation and public safety was one of these six departments. The office of Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety was created on April 8, 1972, by an act passed by the General Assembly. Governor Holton appointed Wayne A. Whitham, a member of the Winchester City Council, as the first Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety. When Whitham took office on July 1, 1972, he was responsible for State Highway Commission, Division of Motor Vehicles, Department of State Police, Highway Safety Division, Office of Emergency Services, Department of Military Affairs, Virginia State Crime Commission and the Law Enforcement Officers Training Standards Commission. The Office has undergone a series of administrative reorganizations since. On April 12, 1976, the Legislature established separate secretariats for transportation and for public safety, effective July 1, 1976. On July 1, 1984, the offices were again combined. Most recently, the Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety was divided into separate secretariats on February 22, 1990. The Secretary of Transportation is a member of the Governor's Cabinet, and is appointed by the governor, subject to confirmation by the General Assembly. The Secretary is responsible to the governor for the Department of Transportation, Department of Rail and Public Transportation, Department of Aviation, Department of Motor Vehicles, Virginia Port Authority and the Motor Vehicle Dealers Board.
Wayne A. Whitham, the first Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety, was reappointed by Governor-elect Miles E. Godwin, Jr., in December 1973 and by Governor-elect John N. Dalton in December 1977. Whitham suffered a heart attack in August 1978 and resigned in December 1978. On June 7, 1984, Whitham died in Richmond, Virginia. Governor Dalton named George M. Walters, a former top executive of the Reynolds Metals Corporation, to succeed Whitham as Secretary of Transportation. Walters served until the end of Dalton's term in January 1982. Governor-elect Charles S. Robb, the first Democrat to be elected governor since 1965, did not retain any of Dalton's cabinet secretaries. Robb appointed Andrew B. Fogarty, Dalton's assistant secretary for financial policy, as Secretary of Transportation. On July 1, 1984, the secretariats of transportation and public safety were combined again. As a result this partial reorganization of state government, Governor Robb appointed Fogarty Secretary of Administration and Franklin E. White, Secretary of Public Safety, assumed Fogarty's Transportation duties. White, who served as a White House liaison official under President Jimmy Carter, resigned in June 1985 to become the New York state commissioner of transportation. He was replaced by Andrew Fogarty who served until the end of the Robb administration. He later served as Governor Gerald L. Baliles chief of staff from August 1986 to October 1989 when he resigned to become a vice president with CSX Corporation.
In December 1985, Governor-elect Gerald L. Baliles, picked Vivian E. Watts, a northern Virginia legislator, as Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety. Watts served until the end of Baliles' term in 1990. In 1995 she was elected to her old seat in the Virginia House of Delegates. On February 22, 1990, the Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety was divided into separate secretariats. Governor L. Douglas Wilder, appointed John G. Milliken, a member of the Arlington County Board of Supervisors, as the Secretary of Transportation. Milliken resigned on December 17, 1993.
In February 1994 Governor George Allen, the first Republican elected governor since 1977, appointed Robert Martinez as Secretary of Transportation. Martinez was born in Cuba and had served as Deputy Administrator for the Marine Administration and Associate Deputy Secretary of Transportation during President George H.W. Bush's administration. At the end of Governor Allen's term in January 1998, Martinez joined the Norfolk Southern Corporation. Shirley Ybarra, deputy Secretary of Transportation in the Allen administration, was named Martinez's successor by Governor-elect James Gilmore. Ybarra previously worked as a special assistant to Transportation Secretary Elizabeth Dole during President Ronald Reagan's administration. Ybarra served until the end of Gilmore's administration in January 2002. Whittington W. Clement, a former lawyer and long-time member of the Virginia House of Delegates representing the City of Danville, was appointed Secretary of Transportation by Governor Mark R. Warner in 2002. Pierce R. Homer, Deputy Secretary of Transportation, replaced Clement in 2005.
Scope and Content
This collection is composed of the administrative, reference, and correspondence files of the Virginia Secretary of Transportation. The files document the substantive activities and policies of the Office of the Secretary of transportation. The records primarily consists of meterial created or recieved and retained as a result of activities related to federal, interstate, state, and local transportation programs.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Correspondence and Subject Files
Contents List
- Series I. Correspondence and Subject Files, 1972-1977., Extent: 6 boxes. (Box 1-6)
  The original order of files has been maintained as they were recieved from the agency, which are generally arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  - Air Transportation System Study, State, 1972-1975. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Virginia Airports, Dulles and Adv Comte on Avia - Meeting 8/17-19, 1972. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Virginia Airports Authority Dulles - Va. Advisory Committee (Meeting), 1973. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Joint Aviation Meeting (The Homestead), 1974. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Aviation Conference, Virginia Beach, 1976. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Aviation Transportation and Airport - Study Commission, 1976. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Automated Data Processing - Miscellaneous, 1974. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Automated Data Processing - Advisory Committee, 1974-1975. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Automated Data Processing, Division of Directors, 1974-1976. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Automated Data Processing - Motor Vehicles, Divison of, 1972-1975. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Automated Data Processing - Policy (Governor and Cabinet), 1974-1976. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Automated Data Processing - Users Board Proposal, 1974. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Automated Data Processing - State Police, Miscellaneous items, 1973-1974. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Automated Data Processing - Taps Computer Center, 1973-1974. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Automated Data Processing - Virginia Plan for Automated Data Processing in state agencies, 1973-1975. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Auditing and Financial Management, 1975. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Airport Security, 1972-1973. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Atlanta, Metropolitan Atlanta Rapid Transit Authority (Kiepper), 1972. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - State Police - E.G. Beard, 1972-1973. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Bicentennial Year, 1974-1975. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Bicentennial - Transportation Agency Projects, 1976. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Bland Correctional Farm - Lime Plant, 1972. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Blumont, Virginia - Drainage Problem, 1973-1974. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Broad Street Station, 1974-1975. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Chesapeake Bay Bridge Tunnel - Meeting, 1972. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Chesapeake - Delaware Canal Railroad Bridge, 1973. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - National Transportation Week - Speech (Chessie System), 1975. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Military Affairs, Department of - Robert S. Chitty, 1973-1975. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Civitan Club, Speech, 1973. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Clifton Forge Public Library, 1972-1974. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Secretary of the Commonwealth, Mrs. Pat Perkinson, 1974-1977. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Commission on State Governmental Management, 1972-1974. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Commission on State Governmental Management - Meeting, 1974. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Commission on State Governmental Management - Management of Virginia State Government, 1972-1973. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Commission on State Governmantal Management - Hearing, 1976. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Commission on State Governmental Management - Information Papers - Transportation and Public Saftey, 1972-1973. (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Commission on State Governmental Management - Legislation, 1976-1977. (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Convict Labor - Use by Highway, 1972-1974. (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Committee on State Department of Transportation - Meeting, San Diego, Ca., 1977. (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Committee on State Department of Transportation - Meeting, Saratoga Springs, Ny., 1972-1973. (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Committee on State Department of Transportation - Meeting, Baltimore, Md., 1976. (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Committee on State Department of Transportation, 1976. (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Transportation: State Department of Transportation - Meeting, Chicago, 1975. (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Transportation: State Department of Transportation - Meeting, Baltimore (Fed Aid Hwy), 1975. (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - State Department of Transportation: Meeting, San Diego, Ca., 1975. (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Tansportation: State Department of Transportation - Meeting, Portland, Or., 1974. (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Transportation: State Department of Transportation - Meeting, Orlando, Fla., 1974. (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Transportation: State Department of Transportation - Meeting, Madison,Wi., 1973. (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Transportation: State Department of Transportation - Meeting, Miami, Fla., 1972. (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Transportation: State Department of Transporation - Meeting, Friendship, 1972. (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Aviation Matters for State Department of Transportation, 1976. (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - State Department of Transportation: Aviation Subcommittee, 1975-1976. (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Cypress Creek Bridge - Smithfield, Va., 1973. (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Delta Nu Alpha - Transportation Fraternity, 1973-1974. (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Great Dismal Swamp, Department of Interior Study, 1973. (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Dulles International Aeroservices, Inc. - Ground-breaking, 1976. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Elko Tract: Henrico County, Virginia., 1973-1976. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Emergency Services - Disasters (Misc.), 1974. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Emergency Services - House Bill 97, 1974. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Emergency Services, Office of - Preparedness and Assistance Act, 1973. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Emergency Services - Hurricane Eloise, 1975. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Emergency Services - Wise County, Va. (Town of Pound) - Flooding, 1975. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Emergency Services - Wind, Flooding, Tornadoes, 1975. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Emergency Services - Prince William, King George, etc. Counties, Virginia., 1974. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Emergency Services - Tornadoes, Storms, 1974. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Emergency Services - Colonial Beach (Damage), 1974-1975. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Emergency Services - Agnes (Flood), 1972. (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Enviroment, Council on, Speech by Wayne A. Whitham, 1975. (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Fair Housing Law for Virginia, 1973. (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Fairfax County Airport - General Aviation (Ft. Belvoir), 1972. (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Fairfax County Airport - Meeting (Pentagon), 1974. (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - FBI Academy Training for Local Law Enforcement Officers, 1976. (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Gammage, Miss Stewart - Commonealth Intern Assigned to Transportation and Public Saftey, 1973-1974. (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Golden Wings Over Richmond - Byrd Field Anniversary Celebration, 1977. (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Governor - Mills E. Godwin, 1974-1977. (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Godwin - Achievements of Second 4 year administration, 1977. (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Governor's Executive Assistant - Jack Davis, 1972-1974. (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Governor - Hon. Linwood Holton, 1974. (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Governor's Management Study - Dr. Richard Powers, 1972-1973. (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Governor and Cabinet - Citizen Tour, 1972. (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Governor's Cabinet - Communications Committee, 1973. (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Governor's Cabinet - Mail Delivery Committee, 1973-1974. (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Governor's Cabinet - Printing Committee, 1973-1974. (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Deputy Assistant to the Cabinet, 1976. (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Cabinet - Ombudsman Committee, 1973. (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - lieutenant Governor - Honorable Henry Howell, 1973. (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Gun Registration, 1973-1975. (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Highway - Federal Aid (Highway act of 1973), 1973. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Highway Saftey Division - Citizen's Band (Emergency Radio Network), 1972. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Highway Saftey Division - Seat belts, 1972-1975. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Highways, Department of Airplane, 1972. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Housing Reloation Programs (Minority Persons Use), 1972-1973. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Interstate 66 - Highway, 1976. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Interstate Commerce Commission Practitioners Association - Speech: Kepner, Tregoe, 1976. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Kresky, Edward M. - Wertheim and Co. Inc. (Study Transportation), 1972-1973. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Leesburg By-Pass, 1972-1974. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Legislation - Transporation, 1976. (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Melchiorre, Peter, 1974. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Manassas Airport, 1972-1974. (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Marshall, Arthur N. - Traffic Saftey Systems, 1974-1976. (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Mentally Handicapped Persons - Use in Highway Programs, 1972-1973. (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Motorist's Aid (Virginia Highway Courtesy Patrol), 1975-1976. (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Department of Motorvehicles - Visual Impairment (Highway Saftey - Dr. James Hall), 1974. (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Motor Vehicles, Division of - hdgrs Bldg no.1, 1974-1975. (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Motor Vehicles, Division of - Hdgrs Bldg no.1, 1972-1973. (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Department of Motor Vehicles - Driver Re-Examination, 1974-1975. (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Department of Motor Vehicles - Accelerated Collection from Dealers, 1975. (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Department of Motor Vehicles - Planning Meeting (Roanoke, Va.), 1976. (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Department of Motor Vehicles - Planning (Meeting), 1974. (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Department of Motor Vehicles - Reorganization, 1975. (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Mountaineer - Amtrak - Norfolk - Cincinnatti, 1977. (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - National Association of State Aviation Officials - Annual Meeting, Norfolk, Va., 1976. (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - No-Fault Auto Insurance, 1974. (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Norfolk - Va. Beach - Urban Mass Transportation Association Technical Study, 1974. (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Norfolk and Southern Rail Road, 1973-1974. (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - O'Neil, Colonel Frederick M., 1973-1974. (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Newport News Shipbuilding and Dry Dock - Dredge, 1973-1974. (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Parking and Commuting - State Employees, 1973-1974. (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Transportation - Virginia Department of Transportation (Miscellaneous), 1972-1973. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - National Transportation Study - Meeting, 1972. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - National Transportation Study, 1974. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Transportation and Public Saftey - Task Force 1972. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - transportation and Public Saftey - Secretary's Staff Meeting, 1972-1974. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Urban High Density Traffic Program (Highway), 1974. (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - University of Virginia - Speech, 1976. (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - University of Virginia and Virginia Polytechnic Institute - Virginia Transportation (Planning and Research Workshop, VPI), 1973. (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Virginia Aviation Conference - The Homestead, 1975. (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Virginia Programs, 1974. (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Virginia Association of Traffic Engineers, 1973-1975. (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Virginia Highway and Transportation Conference - Virginia Military Institute, 1977. (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University - Transportation Researh Projects, 1972-1974. (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Virginia Polytechnic Institute and University of Virginia Steering Committee, 1973-1974. (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Virginia Metropolitan Areas Transportation Study Commission (House Bill 364), 1975. (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Virginia Petroleum Industries - New Orleans, 1974. (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Warrenton By-Pass, 1973. (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Wayside Theater - Middletown, Virginia, 1973-1974. (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Washington and Old Dominion Railroad, 1974. (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Rail - Washington/Richmond Corridor Study (High Speed Passenger Service), 1972-1973. (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Waynesboro JC's - General Wayne Hotel (Speech), 1974. (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Whitham, Wayna A. - Memorandum to Agency Heads, 1972-1976. (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Williams, Ernest Wells - Arlington, Virginia, 1972-1973. (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Winchester Rotary Club - Speech, 1977. (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Youthful Offenders, Services to Youthful Offenders - Study Commission (House Joint Resolution 133), 1972. (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Penn Central Railroad, 1972-1976. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Penn Central - Interstate Commerce Commission (Eastern shore-Northeastern rail road abandonment), 1974. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Penn Central Railroad - Maintenance on Delmarva Line, 1974. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Penn Central - Interstate Commerce Commission (Winchester, Virginia - Martinsburg, West Virginia Abandonment, 1974-1975. (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Photography - Transportation and Public Saftey Committee, 1973. (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Privacy and Security of Information - Cabinet Study, 1974. (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - "PRT" System (People Mover), 1973. (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Recycling, 1973. (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Relocation Assistance - Federal, 1970. (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Richmond - Central Richmond Association, 1973-1974. (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Richmond Metropolitan Authority - Downtown Expressway, 1972. (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Richmond - Petersburg Turnpike, 1972-1977. (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Right Turn on Red, 1975. (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Ruritan Club - Hanover (Speech), 1975. (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - SASHTO Annual Convention, 1976. (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Shared Office Facilities, 1972. (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Shenandoah Airport, 1974. (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Shenandoah Valley Manufacturer's Association, 1973. (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Skyway-to-Highway - Loudon County, 1974. (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Simmons, LD - Waynesboro, Va. (I-64), 1973-1974. (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Smith, Irving P. - Smith and Locke Associates, Inc., 1974. (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - South River Watershed - Flood Control Commission, 1973. (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Speakes, Mrs Herbert F. - Woodbridge, Virginia (Parking problems), 1973. (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - State Police, Department of - Superintendent (Burgess, Colonel), 1972-1976. (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - State Planning and Community Affairs, Division of - Miscellaneous, 1974-1975. (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - State Planning and Community Affais, Division of - Director, 1972-1976. (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Statistical Coordination - Advisory Committee, 1977. (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Staunton, City of, 1972-1973. (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Stranded Motorsts (Emergency serices, miscellaneous), 1972. (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Studded Tires, 1974-1977. (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Temple, T. Edward - Virginia Commonwealth University, 1973-1975. (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Transportation - Dulles International Airport, 1972-1973. (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - National Transportation Week, 1974. (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - Traffic Clubs of Richmond (Speech), 1974. (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - Traffic Records - Information System, 1974-1976. (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - Transportation - Model (Virginia), 1972. (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - Transportation Conference, Virginia (Governor's), 1973. (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - Transportation and Public Saftey - Miscellaneous, 1975. (Box 6, Folder 38)
  - Transportation on Virginia Department of Transportation (Frank E. Mann - subcommittee), 1973-1974. (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - Transportation, Department of, Virginia (Working File 1973 Bill), 1972-1973. (Box 6, Folder 40)